<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="https://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="en-IN"><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><break time="1s"/><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>A borrower repays perfectly and still disappoints the investor. She sells her home, closes the mortgage years early, and returns every rupee owed. Credit performed. The investment changed because time changed.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Another borrower also performs perfectly but never prepays. Market rates rise, the mortgage remains outstanding, and the investor waits much longer than expected. Again, no default. This time the disappointment comes from extension rather than contraction.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Securitisation carries several clocks. Borrowers choose when unscheduled principal returns. Legal maturity sets the final boundary. Note rules allocate principal. Markets decide whether the security can be financed or sold meanwhile.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Begin with scheduled principal. The mortgage contract gradually reduces balance under its amortisation schedule. Unscheduled principal arrives when borrowers refinance, move, or otherwise repay early.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Models need a language for that unscheduled behaviour. The Public Securities Association convention, spoken as <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub>, supplies a standard mortgage prepayment curve for comparison.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>At one hundred <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub>, the annualised conditional prepayment rate begins low, rises by zero-point-two percentage points each month, reaches six percent in month thirty, and remains there. The ramp represents a convention about seasoning, not a promise from homeowners.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Fifty <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub> applies half that benchmark. Two hundred <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub> applies twice it. The number tells analysts how an assumption relates to the standard curve.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Conditional prepayment rate is annualised. Single monthly mortality, spoken as S M M, converts the assumption to a monthly rate. At six percent annual C P R, the monthly rate is slightly above one-half of one percent.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>The calculation applies to the remaining pool. Original balance is not prepaid repeatedly. Scheduled amortisation, earlier prepayment, and default continually change the base.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Seasoning determines where loans sit in their lives. New borrowers rarely refinance on the first morning. After time passes, changing rates, moves, cash windfalls, and life events create more opportunities to prepay.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Rate incentive is powerful but incomplete. Falling market rates encourage refinancing. Closing cost, credit quality, loan size, documentation, borrower inertia, and property value create friction.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Burnout appears after repeated opportunities. Borrowers most able and willing to refinance may already have left. The remaining pool can respond less strongly to the next rate decline.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Faster prepayment creates contraction risk. Principal returns early, weighted average life shortens, and future interest disappears. Investors reinvest when replacement yields may be lower.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Slower prepayment creates extension risk. Principal remains outstanding, duration lengthens, and the investor stays exposed when market yields may be higher elsewhere.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>A premium investor generally dislikes unexpectedly fast principal because less time remains to earn enough interest above par. A discount investor may welcome principal returning at par sooner, subject to the rest of the risk.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The same prepayment curve affects different tranches differently. Sequential rules can use early principal to reduce senior notes. Planned-amortisation classes, support classes, and other designs can redistribute timing, but none controls the borrower.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Default must remain separate. Prepayment returns principal. Default removes performing balance and may return only a recovery later. Combining them would make a credit loss sound like early success.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Now place these mortgages in Chennai and Mumbai. We do not assign a borrowed American <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub> speed and call the work finished. We collect local loan age, rates, refinancing behaviour, turnover, borrower type, channel, and historical prepayment.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub> can remain a comparison ruler. Calibration must come from the pool and market being analysed. Convention organises assumptions; evidence chooses them.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The investor now faces another clock. The security is paying, but financing markets freeze. Dealers quote wide spreads, lenders demand larger haircuts, and buyers hoard cash.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>During the financial crisis, this kind of funding stress damaged asset-backed issuance and trading. Consumer-credit collateral and market liquidity could weaken together, but they were not the same problem.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The Federal Reserve announced the Term Asset-Backed Securities Loan Facility, or <sub alias="T A L F">TALF</sub>, in November two thousand eight to support issuance of eligible asset-backed securities tied to consumer and small-business credit.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>An eligible investor could pledge qualifying securities for term funding under program rules. The financing helped investors carry assets and supported demand for new issuance.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The borrower payments still came from auto loans, card receivables, student loans, small-business loans, or other eligible collateral under the relevant terms. <sub alias="T A L F">TALF</sub> did not substitute Federal Reserve cash for every missed instalment.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Haircuts required the investor to fund part of the collateral value. A larger haircut meant less public lending against the same security and more investor equity at risk.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The loan was non-recourse subject to program conditions. That limited the lender&apos;s claim rather than turning the collateral into a guaranteed asset. Eligibility, valuation, haircut, and collateral performance remained essential.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice></speak>
<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="https://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="en-IN"><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Imagine an eligible auto-loan security worth one hundred. A facility lends ninety and the investor supplies ten. If security value falls modestly, investor equity absorbs it first. If collateral loss becomes severe, the protection can be exceeded.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The security already contains its own enhancement, such as subordination or reserves. The facility haircut sits outside that capital structure. Adding the two casually would mix protection for different claims.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Now accelerate auto-loan prepayment. The pledged security shortens and principal returns. Funding may repay earlier, and the investor must redeploy cash. Timing changed without credit loss.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Slow prepayment instead. The security extends toward or beyond the investor&apos;s funding horizon. A mismatch can reappear even when every borrower remains current.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Facility maturity, security expected life, and legal final maturity therefore belong in the same timeline. Funding stability is strongest when the asset cannot unexpectedly outlive the financing without a plan.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Add actual borrower defaults. Enhancement absorbs some loss, note cash weakens, market value falls, and the haircut cushion is tested. Liquidity support can reduce forced selling; it cannot manufacture recovery.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Add market panic without collateral deterioration. Prices may fall because buyers cannot finance positions and sellers need cash. A facility can address that market-function problem more directly.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Add both at once and attribution becomes difficult. Price reflects expected loss, uncertainty, liquidity premium, financing scarcity, duration, and forced sales. One market quote contains several stories.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Securities disclosure helps separate them by showing collateral, performance, servicing, structure, maturity, and risks. <sub alias="P S A">PSA</sub> helps organise timing assumptions. <sub alias="T A L F">TALF</sub> illustrates a funding response. None is a complete investment conclusion alone.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>The Federal Reserve source establishes the historical United States facility and its purpose. Sifma establishes the prepayment convention. Neither should be presented as an Indian rule or imported without context.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Return to our first homeowner. Her early repayment reduces credit exposure and returns principal safely. The investor&apos;s reinvestment problem is real even though the borrower deserves praise.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Return to the second homeowner. His slow but perfect payment extends the security. Duration risk is real even though credit remains strong.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>Return to the frozen market. A perfectly current security can become difficult to sell or finance. Liquidity risk is real even when contractual cash has not failed.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Return to the defaulted pool. A liquid market can price and trade the security efficiently while expected loss remains high. Liquidity cannot be used as a synonym for quality.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>A complete judgement therefore maps borrower timing into collateral principal, collateral principal into tranche life, tranche life into investor duration, and duration into funding needs. It then maps default and recovery separately.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Move the reasoning to education loans. Graduates may prepay after salary increases, extend through permitted terms, or default after unemployment. Investors may also face a market that refuses to finance the securities. Four clocks, four different consequences.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p>The album began with one future payment becoming funding today. It ends with the recognition that every future payment also carries a date, and dates can change value even when the amount is ultimately paid.</p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p>Credit asks whether cash arrives. Duration asks when. Liquidity asks whether the claim can be financed or sold while we wait. Good securitisation analysis never lets one answer impersonate the other two.</p><break time="260ms"/></voice></speak>
