<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="https://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="en-IN"><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><break time="1s"/><p><s>Money comes into a securitisation in one form and leaves in another.</s> <s>Borrower collections arrive as principal, interest, fees, recoveries, and sometimes late payments.</s> <s>Investors receive whatever the transaction rules allow them to receive.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>During the two thousand eight to two thousand nine market freeze, that difference mattered.</s> <s>Assets could still be paying while the market questioned the timing, priority, and liquidity of the securities built from them.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The loan matters, but the fight is over what happens to the cash after it arrives.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>The payment order decides who gets paid, who waits, and whose protection is being used.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>The market freeze in two thousand eight and two thousand nine exposed how quickly payment priority and funding access can matter more than a familiar asset label.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The line of succession to the Iron Throne is not a perfect analogy, but the priority logic is exact: one pot of value can support many claimants, and the order of entitlement determines who waits when the pot is too small.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Start with a pass through structure.</s> <s>Borrower collections, after permitted deductions, are passed to investors with limited reshaping.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>What risk does the investor accept in a pass through?</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Pass through means the investor receives the collateral cash without structural risk.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>It gives the investor a more direct exposure to collateral timing, prepayment, default, servicing, and recovery.</s> <s>It does not remove fees, collection risk, or liquidity risk.</s> <s>The investor may receive principal earlier or later than expected, and the value of that timing depends on reinvestment conditions.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Direct exposure is not the same as complete transparency.</s> <s>The cash still passes through accounts and rules.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>A pay through structure reshapes collateral collections into a designed payment profile.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Why does reshaping cash flow create both value and dependence?</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Once the issuer designs the payment schedule, collateral timing no longer matters.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>The issuer can create different maturities and payment priorities, but the design depends on collateral performance, reserves, triggers, and assumptions.</s> <s>A promise to pay investors on a schedule is credible only if collections, liquidity, and enhancement can support it when the pool behaves differently from the base case.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Reshaping timing can make a security useful.</s> <s>It can also make the structure more dependent on the rules doing exactly what the documents say.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Now follow the ordinary waterfall.</s> <s>Collections may pay taxes, servicing fees, trustee fees, interest, principal, reserves, and residual claims in a stated order.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Why is saying “fees, interest, then principal” not enough?</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice></speak>
<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="https://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="en-IN"><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><break time="450ms"/><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>The sequence is obvious, so a high level description captures the risk.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The actual terms decide which account receives the money, which deductions are permitted, how reserves are funded, how shortfalls are allocated, and whether excess cash reaches junior or residual claims.</s> <s>A one line summary can hide the point where the investor actually loses control of cash.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>A waterfall must be traced like a transaction, not recited like a heading.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The stress case changes the conversation.</s> <s>A trigger can stop replenishment, redirect excess spread, move the deal to sequential principal, or increase reserve funding.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>What does a trigger do economically?</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>A trigger is just a warning indicator for the investor report.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>A trigger is a contractual state change.</s> <s>It can alter payment priority, control rights, amortisation, reserve requirements, or the use of excess cash.</s> <s>The important question is not whether the trigger was breached.</s> <s>It is what cash flow moved after the breach and which claim absorbed the pressure.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The waterfall is normal only until the contract says it is not.</s> <s>Then the trigger becomes the transaction.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Let us make one collection tangible.</s> <s>A borrower pays one hundred rupees.</s> <s>That does not mean an investor receives one hundred rupees.</s> <s>The documents may first pay taxes, a servicer, a trustee, hedging costs, overdue expenses, interest, reserve top-ups, and principal.</s> <s>The residual may see nothing.</s> <s>On a bad month, the order matters more than the total collection.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>And you cannot read that order like a school timetable.</s> <s>You have to ask what changes when collections are lower than expected.</s> <s>Does interest get deferred?</s> <s>Does principal stop flowing to junior notes?</s> <s>Does excess spread get trapped?</s> <s>Does the deal switch from sharing principal across classes to paying one class first?</s> <s>Those are economic decisions written into contract language.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>The phrase “the waterfall protects the senior note” is incomplete until you can say how much cash it protects, for how long, and what has to happen before the protection moves.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>That is why a trigger matters.</s> <s>It is not an alarm bell in a monthly report.</s> <s>It is a switch.</s> <s>When it trips, someone who expected cash may wait, and someone who thought they had time may discover that the deal has changed its priorities.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>I would never approve a deal after reading only the base case payment schedule.</s> <s>I want the same schedule after a missed collection, after a reserve breach, after a servicer advance fails, and after a trigger flips the deal into a different mode.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>That is how you find the investor’s real position.</s> <s>On paper, two notes may both pay eight percent.</s> <s>Under stress, one may have interest deferred, another may stop receiving principal, and the residual may be shut out entirely.</s> <s>The coupon alone does not tell you who bears the pressure.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice></speak>
<speak version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/synthesis" xmlns:mstts="https://www.w3.org/2001/mstts" xml:lang="en-IN"><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><break time="450ms"/><p><s>So we should talk about accounts as well as classes.</s> <s>Cash can be in a collection account, a reserve account, a principal account, or a distribution account.</s> <s>The label on the account matters only when the documents say who controls it and what it can be used for.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Exactly.</s> <s>Read the payment date rules closely enough that you can say where the next rupee goes if the month is worse than expected.</s> <s>That is a far better test than reciting the order of the notes.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Run one ordinary month.</s> <s>The pool collects one hundred rupees.</s> <s>Assume five goes to tax and servicing, four goes to trustee and other senior costs, twelve goes to note interest, ten refills a reserve, and the remaining sixty-nine is available for principal.</s> <s>Those numbers are only an illustration.</s> <s>The point is that the investor who hears “the pool collected one hundred” still does not know what they receive.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Now make the month worse.</s> <s>Collections fall to seventy.</s> <s>The same fees may still be due.</s> <s>Interest may be senior to principal.</s> <s>The reserve may be below its required amount.</s> <s>The junior note may receive nothing even though borrowers are still paying.</s> <s>This is why cash flow is not a straight line from borrower to investor.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Then the trigger trips.</s> <s>The deal may stop buying new receivables.</s> <s>Excess spread may be trapped.</s> <s>Principal may go sequentially to the senior note.</s> <s>The language in the report might say “early amortisation” or “performance trigger.”</s> <s>The economic meaning is simpler: the deal has changed who waits and who gets protected.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>When you read a waterfall, take one payment date and work it line by line.</s> <s>Name the account that receives cash.</s> <s>Name the test that must be met.</s> <s>Name the class that receives the next rupee.</s> <s>If you cannot do that, you have not read the payment terms yet.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>The Iron Bank would trace the payment order before trusting the headline collection number.</s> <s>The amount of cash is only the beginning; priority determines whose claim is actually paid.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>All right.</s> <s>Here is the situation.</s> <s>Borrower collections are arriving, but not in the amount or timing investors expected.</s> <s>Trace the cash and decide which payment rule changes first.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Work it through aloud.</s> <s>Start with the cash flow, the legal claim, the timing, and the failure condition.</s> <s>A rating or a product label can wait.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>Apply the exercise to an Indian auto loan transaction receiving collections from Chennai and Hyderabad.</s> <s>Ask how the payment order changes when collections arrive late or the pool enters an early amortisation state.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice><voice name="en-IN-Meera:DragonHDLatestNeural"><p><s>Trace one unit of collection through the normal waterfall and then through a trigger state.</s> <s>Name the first deduction, the first protected claim, the first exposed claim, and the cash that no longer reaches the residual.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></voice><voice name="en-IN-Diya:DragonHDLatestNeural"><mstts:express-as style="calm" styledegree="0.4"><prosody rate="-1%"><p><s>You understand the deal when you can explain the cash, name the assumption, and follow the consequence to the investor who has to live with it.</s></p><break time="260ms"/></prosody></mstts:express-as></voice></speak>
